or pushed it if you're a Russian good
thing I didn't leave the meeting yeah no
don't leave the meeting that would be
all over hey everyone and welcome to
Chef AJ live I'm your host Chef AJ and
this is where I introduce you to amazing
people like you who are doing great
things in the world that I think you
should know about well we're closing in
on the last 10 hours of the ultimate raw
vegan bundle it only happens once a year
it's all new content even if you got a
bundle before you don't have this one
and to save the best for last we have
one of the co what do you call it
co-creators of the bundle Chris Kendall
who's going to be making an authentic
raw vegan Ethiopian lentil stew please
welcome him to the show how you doing
Chris
oh bless uh way way too kind thank you
so much I'm I'm doing great it's been an
amazing bundle party Italian jam-packed
with lots of lives and connection and
happy people enjoying the bundle already
and my happy little snooter cat mowing
around so it's been awesome how about
you good well raw people are nice
well you started off nice
your cat is we all have our pets with us
today on today's show I've got little
Bailey here as my co-host so I don't
even know what what the recipe is
whether it's raw or vegan so maybe talk
about what it is when it's not raw or
vegan and how you first made it vegan
and made it maybe then made it raw maybe
you made it raw vegan all at the same
time
awesome yeah you know this all stemmed
back from when I was living in Vancouver
and I first went vegan uh in
2003-ish yeah 2003 and Ethiopian was the
last Cuisine that I actually had eaten
uh before I ventured into fully a fully
raw food diet and I loved it I used to
go I was living in Vancouver I'd go to
East Indian buffets and that was my
all-time favorite but then I discovered
the Ethiopian buffets and I just fell in
love I loved all those Curry flavors and
all the different textures and the
injera and all that kind of stuff and I
even tried by hand at making injera I
used to do a bunch of different ferments
and all those fun things but then when I
first went raw vegan in 2004
I really went simple simple hygienic
rubbing in yours is really fruits and
vegetables I dropped all onions and
spices and all that stuff for a good
period of time and I thought I kissed
all those old flavors and dishes goodbye
but as time went on and I wrote a book
and I started the raw advantage and
started Consulting I saw a definite need
not only out there but also Within
Myself to explore some different old
favorites and while I'd like to say that
this is a recipe that I've been
developing for 12 years or 15 years I
actually when I started making this
stews book is called Cravings Busters
sweet and savory stews I just thought I
want to make some of the most classic
foods from around the world and slip a
couple kind of curry-like stews in there
because they're some of my favorite
dishes in the world right so
this just came from thinking about those
old flavors and I've been introduced to
one of my favorite spices in the world
if not my favorite Barber and I thought
I want to make a classic Ethiopian
Berber based stew and that's when this
became known as the lentil and want what
is the uh the cooked cabbage that's what
they typically call them and it is all
100 raw vegan though and it's really
delicious and I'm sure it'll knock
people's socks off and they won't think
it's raw or vegan nice well that is
incredible you know did you
become raw before becoming vegan or at
the same time
well my transition from like junk food
drinking smoking eating the grossest
stuff possible to high raw vegan was
about a four and a half year transition
and then I went High raw vegan where I
was eating fruit for breakfast and fruit
for lunch and then a simple cooked
dinner I like to you know bake sweet
potatoes and broccolis and you know do
all my own ferments and sourdoughs and
stuff like that but that was only for
about a six year period where I was uh
strictly vegan and high raw and then
during that six month period I was
actually in school to become a holistic
nutritionist and in the middle of that
schooling I went to a vegan Health
Festival where there was three different
raw food teachers I went to one and it
was good I went to another and it blew
my head open it was Dr Doug RAM and I
know he's been on your show before and
there's just something about him AJ he
was glowing and the things he was saying
just got my inner no one Bell kind of
going off like this makes sense this is
it that's that last key that I needed to
go all raw because before that I
couldn't quite figure it out I had read
some books I tried I could never stay
raw but literally the day after I met
Doug I went 100 raw and my entire life
changed you know I think I told you this
before but I've been studying nutrition
for about five years and I was in school
for it but I had zero intention of ever
doing anything work-wise for it I never
wanted to be in front of the camera I
didn't want to be on stage but when I
went for all my heart center burst open
and my mind just was like click this is
what you're here for and ever since then
I've been on this path of discovering
more and more and learning more about
the raw food lifestyle and holistic
health and now 13 years I've been doing
this full time well thank you what is a
registered holistic nutritionist and
where does one get educated for that
title so I went to this the Canadian
School of natural nutrition in Canada
it's one of the biggest Natural Health
Schools out there and they have uh
in-house and online classes and I know
it's been a little while since I checked
in on them but I know at one point they
had at least a handful of schools across
Canada and they have various course
offerings and the one I went for back in
2003 starting and graduating 2004 was uh
the registered holistic nutritionist uh
certification and so that was a one-year
full-time course that really goes into
depth with physiology and anatomy and
multiple different types of diets and
all the different aspects of holistic
health to create a union of Body Mind
and Spirit and then they also really
taught us how to do consultations and
how to do nutritional essays and create
meal plans and connect with people so
so that's kind of what that's all about
nice are you the one that invented that
technique of freezing the vegetables raw
and then making them give them more of
like a cooked texture when defrosting
was that your brainchild
well I Won't Say I'm the one who created
freezing vegetables but I'm definitely
as far as I understand it the one that
had popularized in raw food and utilized
it for a bunch of different dishes and
textures so
um I'll I'll claim that status uh at
least since you brought it up how did
you know that it was going to do that
like how did you figure that out you
know what was the first one I did
um the first one that I did was actually
broccoli and no cauliflower because I
always really liked making cauliflower
curries you know the the Indian curries
were always my favorite aloo gobi and
for multiple years I would just either
use raw cauliflower or I'd put it in a
bowl of really warm water like as close
to Boiling as I could do without feeling
like I was incredibly bad kid and
spanking myself or lashing myself later
and it was good it softens it a little
bit but one time I think I just had
extra cauliflower and I just put it in
the freezer and when I took it out I was
like holy crap this is seriously like an
amazing cooked food texture and I
noticed it even feels like it digests a
little bit better and that that kind of
got that in there and then I started
experimenting with other vegetables and
put up videos and you know started
talking about it and mentioning it and I
had never seen it in the raw food scene
and other people hadn't really heard
about it either so
um yeah I just started doing it more and
more and this book kind of takes it to
the next level where I really explored a
bunch of different ingredients and found
the ones that really worked the best in
different ways to achieve the most
cooked food like tastes and textures
with a whole bunch of different
ingredients
nice well when you think about it you
know just frozen vegetables that you buy
in the store their texture is different
than Fresh So they kind of been freezing
vegetables for a long time
for sure but the one difference is when
you buy vegetables uh Frozen in the
store they do blanch them first to kill
any bacteria on the outside and also to
retain the color so when you freeze them
yourself you don't have to blanch them
if you want you can but you don't have
to and they still work really well it's
just they won't have quite as long as a
shelf life and they would retain their
colors along but for the most part when
I'm doing this I'm I'm freezing them and
using them within a couple weeks or
maybe a couple months Max and then
they're still perfectly fine
and it is nice because it's the best
method of preservation in terms of
nutrient loss so it it really works
really well when you have extra and if
you can get an amazing deal and then the
bonuses that hey it tastes even more and
feels even more like a cooked food dish
yeah clever
well tell us what we have to do to make
this why is it called wat stew what stew
yeah it's kind of fun right lentil wants
to and unless I'm completely mistaken
from my understanding
um there's a lot of different watts in
uh in Ethiopian cuisine and it simply
just means a cabbage based Curry so they
have different names for the different
vegetables and a what Curry or stew is
just cabbage based so that's really the
big bulk of this recipe here we have uh
about 0.75 pounds or 345 grams of really
nice brush and then chopped cabbage that
I froze overnight and I do want to
mention that
it works absolutely the best if the
ingredients you're using are really
fresh high water content and crispy
because the reason that they give that
uh kind of cooked food texture is the
water in the cells expands ruptures the
cells and then softens the cell walls
and you know it just creates a little
bit of a softer a little bit more
pliable cooked food taste and texture so
if you have really dry old cabbage you
do it it may not freeze properly and it
might still be really crunchy and sure
that's tasty but it's not the same
texture that we're really looking for to
make this authentic
good to know
so if we'll jump right into this then
we're going to start with the
ingredients that we froze will say if
someone was going to make this tomorrow
because unfortunately if you don't have
stuff prepped you're probably not going
to achieve the same tastes if you just
started right now so again we took about
uh 0.75 pounds or 345 grams of cabbage I
chopped it into cubes whatever style you
like but I like cubes and I put in the
freezer and if you think ahead you can
take it out in the morning let it thaw
on your counter you can put in the
dehydrator and dry it there but a lot of
the times I don't think that far enough
ahead and I just put it in a bowl and I
thought with some warm water and then I
drain it off in a colander
so so we have the Cabbage that we
started last night we have some carrots
we have uh 115 grams or about a quarter
of a pound and same thing the carrots
when you freeze them and thaw them they
get a little bit softer they get a
little bit brighter you can see they
look cooked and they actually get a
little bit sweeter and that's the same
as a lot of the frozen vegetables they
get a little bit sweeter a little softer
and a little easier to digest so we're
going to put that in the bowl as well
very classic in Ethiopian cuisine
cabbage and carrots
then
one of my favorites we have some red
onion we did the same it's about 50
grams of red onion some people find
onion a little bit strong you know a
little bit irritating and if you cut it
I know a lot of people know if you cut
it let it sit out the mustard oil
dissipates it becomes a little less
irritating a little more mild in flavor
and then if you freeze them I mean look
at this it's seriously it's like oh
where are we it's like sauteed onions
they're like translucent and soft and
milder in flavor
so I love doing that and we just put
those in the bowl too
yeah yeah
I was thinking though because sometimes
I buy onion already cut and I do that
because it is milder so that would make
sense what you just said
yeah it works really well because it
does just mellow the flavor and reduces
the mustard oil content which is it is a
little bit irritating you know sometimes
if you eat a lot of onion you get a
little bit of mucus and you know of
course your eyes get uh irritated
because that mustard oil is coming off
of the onion right so
this is just a way to make it even more
mellow and then when I wash it or uh
thaw it in some warm water that at the
same time also kind of removes a little
bit of that it just makes them a little
bit mellower so it's kind of a nice
option because you still get a lot of
the nutrition and all the other
nutrients that are in there it just
makes them a bit mellower
so last but not least is the lentils
because of course this is a sprouted
lentil uh watt you know and so we have I
guess technically be a doll but uh that
maybe that's an Indian anyhow we just
have little baby red uh red lentil
sprouts and I mean I don't know how easy
this is going to be to see but there's
just an itty bitty teeny tail growing
off there I actually just started these
yesterday and that's one of the reasons
I really also like the red lentils you
want to get really good quality red
lentils because some of them won't
Sprout and you don't want split lentils
but if you get good quality sproutable
red lentils you can just soak them
overnight and let them sit uh you know
once you've drained them for like a
couple hours and they'll they'll Sprout
up nice just a little bit you can let
them Sprout for a few days if you like
but my preference is just a little tail
and then I actually also put these in
the freezer for six hours and it just
softens them even more makes them a
little sweeter and makes them taste like
a cooked lentil rather than a fresh
crunchy sprouted lentil which I love too
for different dishes but for this one I
wanted to taste like a really authentic
cooked lentil so
I had this all in here and the last
thing I'll mention about all this is I
really like this technique for some of
these recipes not all the recipes in the
stew book have Frozen ingredients
Bunches of them are crunchy as well but
for certain ones I wanted a uniform
textures like this and it's a really fun
way too to pre-prep because you know you
can look at the recipes and you can prep
a whole bunch of individual portions of
all these ingredients throw them in the
freezer and then you know you have
almost ready-made meals within 10
minutes just taking them out thawing and
making a sauce and
um I often with lentils do big batches
of lentils and then just freeze them in
portion size like a cup or two cups this
was actually uh what do we have here one
cup of sprouted red lentils or about 200
grams so we have all these main
ingredients in the bowl and you can just
do a little stir up and we got a little
snooter meowing around
yeah you hear that little snoozer
how do you want to say hi how many cats
do you have
I have two cats oh it's a little snoozer
she's so good such a beautiful face
you're in Sweden what time is it is it
like the middle of the night now it's 11
30 now I guess or 11 something okay I'll
get you I'll get you to bed before
midnight it's all right with this bundle
craziness AJ I've been up to like four
almost every night is this is your third
bundle co-producing isn't it a fourth
actually for the ultimate raw vegan
bundle which I've been a part of some
others but I'm behind the scenes doing
the customer service and you know all
the for some of my own promo well
scooter so I'll just grab my blender
because I forgot it over there and it's
got to go downstairs there we go
oh there we go I got it
and then we can make the beautiful oh of
course I left my little over there too
how embarrassing
forgot my lid
and we can blend up the rest of the
ingredients so that's all we're doing
for the chunky bits
but for the actual
stew base we're gonna take one pound of
tomatoes
the better the quality of the tomatoes
the better this is going to taste
and then I got a whole bunch of
ingredients here so right here we have
uh about a table what would we say it
was a tablespoon of Ginger or just like
a nice little thumb
about
40 grams of dates or about two medjool
but these are smaller so I have like
four of these small soft dates
and then two tablespoons one tablespoon
of hemp seeds one of my favorite seeds
in the world I love hemp seeds so it's a
really low-fat dip but it's pretty darn
filling and it's actually pretty high
calorie this whole dish here is going to
be about 819 calories those lentils
really boost the calories and uh work
really well so we have those and no
Ethiopian Curry actually this variety of
Curry would be complete without some
Berber so we have the Berber
[Music]
just one tablespoon have you ever tried
maryborough before I don't think so I
I've seen it and I thought it was
pronounced Burberry but it's Berber okay
well you know what I could be totally
wrong
the best for Bear you probably have it
right
uh I I wouldn't Bank on that I'll be
honest
I'm not shy to be wrong I tell you but
I'll let you know if I am so there we go
we put that in there we just have one
tablespoon of the bearberry or the
berber and I do have a Berber recipe
which I'll bring right up to the screen
at the end so you can even screenshot it
it's a bonus in the book but I'll just
Chris Chris you gave it to me I put it
in the Showbox that was so kind of you
perfect awesome so then I got a couple
different spices up here I got uh one
teaspoon of garlic powder I often like
to use a garlic powder rather than the
the whole garlic I just find it a little
bit milder and a little bit more like a
slight roasted kind of flavor
speaking of roasted we have some smoked
paprika which very interestingly a lot
of people think that smoked paprika
would be cooked but they actually smoke
it under low heat so it doesn't actually
cook it and they smoke it traditionally
for like 48 Hours under a low heat did
not know that really nice one of my
favorites for sure and then last but
definitely not least one teaspoon of
cumin I love cumin it's one of my
favorites ever and this is black cumin
seed which is my favorite
and you know what that's it all we got
to do is blend this up and our magic is
done
so I'm going to put this guy from there
and I even you know my new Vitamix here
it's the accent uh a3500 my biochef
vacuum container works on it so it's
really awesome I can actually vacuum
this up
and there we go
have you tried vacuum blending since I
was on your shoulders I mean but Liss is
always talking about it and John Kohler
too
it's about time I tell you AJ get on get
on the vacuum train with us come on give
it a go
you can all tune it together
so we'll get this Blended up I like to
make it uh oh gosh there we go I like to
make it pretty darn smooth if I can
but let's see
so apologies
get the blender dead
thank you
all right so that's pretty good oh yum
whoa I tell you this can be hard not to
eat at midnight oh no you can't and I
could eat before bed yeah
yeah there is one last thing that we're
going to add in here just to add in some
extra flavor and nutrient density 50
grams of arugula one of my favorite
greens out there holy smokes
so
being lazy I'm just going to throw it
directly in here
and use this spoon to make sure it
doesn't just get to the design
and then we just briefly publish it into
the dish oh you're going to pulse it in
not serve it over
no exactly I don't want to turn the
sauce like green and I want it just to
be almost like I'm uh just or chopping
it really fine like another herb but
I am lazy and instead of chopping I just
let the Vitamix do the trick
so let it go
for one or two
a couple couple pulses
there we go as easy as can be
and
just like that that was pretty darn
quick wasn't it yep
just like that we've had a very
authentic tasting
Ethiopian lentil watch
pour it in top oh get in there no
I'm not gonna take the time to get it
all in because that might just take
forever and
we'll stir this up
the flavors and the smells are just
ridiculous I tell you
wow
and that's just chock full of
deliciousness and of course we got a
wide range of veggies and the lentils
and
there we go
so that's
that's it right there that was really
easy to make
yep super quick and easy and like I said
you know like
if you make some of the stew recipes and
you like them oh yeah like make three
portions at once and then just put them
in plastic bags in the freezer or put
them in your glass tupperwares or
whatever you like and then boom you can
throw something together really quick it
doesn't have to take a lot of time
and uh batch making it that way just
makes it so much quicker
that was great tell us more about the
bundle your offerings all the other
offerings that you remember off the top
of your head because they only have
about uh seven and a half more hours to
get it or maybe it's eight and a half
I'm not good at math but till midnight
Pacific time tonight yeah exactly so
it's a pretty ridiculous offer we have
40 new books that have never been before
released so it's launching directly in
the bundle and actually that's not
totally accurate there's 40 Resources
with about six uh mini courses so it's a
bunch of ebooks and then mini courses
diving into recipes mindfulness there's
a couple yoga courses in there one's in
Ashtanga Yoga course the other one's a
yin yoga course there's a emotional
Freedom there's entrepreneurship
teaching you how to create a business in
the vegan Niche I got a snooter
um Liz has got her wrapped book in there
which is ridiculous actually called hand
salads got a whole bunch of uh
whole bunch of sweets and treats and
delicious smoothies and it's it's really
really jam-packed with a whole bunch of
different resources that is sure to meet
everyone in their flavors or in their
holistic health Journey because you know
it's not just raw food it's got a lot of
different aspects of Health in there and
uh yeah I'm sure anyone who checks it
out is going to be completely blown away
yeah Yin Ross Chef Ian was on the show
earlier in the week and she has like a
dessert book yeah Asian sweets and
treats and it's ridiculously good as
well I actually made her durian cookies
I don't know if you like durian but if
you do then you would love these durian
cookies it was absolutely ridiculous I
just made a pad thai from Emma Raymond
the other night and yeah there's uh
almost too many to remember at least
when you're sleep deprived
uh well hey in a few hours it'll all be
over
yeah I'm gonna be a little sad I tell
you you know it's been an amazing
amazing time I was telling Alyssa
earlier that you know before this
started with the couple months of really
kind of diving deeper into the keyboard
getting things ready and making the
recipes I got a little bit low energy
and then coming together with ever on
these lives and coming together as a
community has really boosted me up and
revitalized my purpose and passion and I
just feel really connected and really
feel blessed to be a part of this
uh well thank you for including me I
have a book in the bundle that I
co-wrote with Lissa it's our volume two
raw food made easy so you can check that
out
which looks ridiculously amazing as well
I was looking at some of the bloom rice
recipes in there and a couple other
really delicious ones looks awesome
anything that Alyssa touches is going to
be amazing so it's been a such a
privilege to be able to work with her
and you on these bundles because you
just make stuff so yummy
it definitely reciprocated absolutely
blessed your part and I feel so lucky
and blessed to be in this together with
Alyssa and everyone who's contributed
and taken part and to see it Ripple out
so many people saying they're really
loving the bundle and you know it's
funny AJ because
we've had a lot of testimonials and
people saying that this bundle
completely changed their life and change
their family's lives and we've also had
a lot of contributors who said you know
I've been raw foodist for five years 10
years but since coming into the bundle
and really seeing you know the
congruency between a whole bunch of
people have been doing this long term
and getting a lot of great information
it's really streamlined my raw food
lifestyle and made the whole thing a lot
easier and better too so testimonials
from inside the bundle and outside the
bundle and we're just trying to grow
this family and create that sweet juicy
wave to cross the peoples
nice hey there's a question from
Stephanie what does Chris eat in a day
oh wow well that's a great question it
depends upon the season but for the most
part when I'm hungry I'm eating fruit
and a lot of the times it's a big banana
smoothie or lately I've been drinking a
lot of melon and orange smoothies so for
example I have these guys down here and
a whole bunch of Mandarin oranges and I
take usually about two of these about
six of these and blend that up for a
nice orange creamsicle for lunch
dinner often starts with fruit and then
goes into something like this or a salad
or a curry
I usually eat two meals a day both of
them usually involve fruit but one of
them at least has a bunch of vegetables
in it
sometimes I ate three meals a day
sometimes I just eat fruit and a little
bit of greens but you know my diet is
predominantly fruit calorically and then
I eat a pretty darn large volume of
vegetables often one or two or three
pounds a day
good for you for including your veggies
I'm a big veggie guy I tell you you know
I I eat a whole bunch more than most I
think oftentimes because like this guy
here this is probably like uh I guess
looking at it I could kind of get
Venture a guess but it's about like two
and a half pounds I tried to make this
dues about that size which for a lot of
people is pretty big and it's something
that's pretty good to work up to if
you're looking to thrive on a long-term
100 raw diet to include a fair amount
quite a bit at least one to two pounds
of vegetables a day
I often eat almost double this you know
sometimes I eat a five or six pound stew
but I'm really darn hungry but um more
often than not I'm also just having like
two liters of smoothie whatever it is
bananas or melons or whole bunches of
mangoes or I have a probably about 10
kilos of grapes in my fridge right now
so a lot of times and just open up clam
shells and eating grapes and I like to
enjoy all of it wow well thank you so
much and guys jump on the bundle when
it's gone it's gone you're gonna miss
making all those hand salads and all
those other fun things do you still
skateboard a lot
heck yeah I do indeed I love it I'm I'm
pushing myself to put up a new video
part in the next couple years here and
uh I'm very blessed to be skateboarding
for a company called totally rad
skateboards and pro for them and a bunch
of different clothing and stuff like
that and I'm going for a surgery on this
the 8th of next month to remove some
Hardware from my ankle and I'm expecting
to kind of bounce back from that even
stronger because it's been giving you a
little bit of ankle problems having this
plate on my ankle
nice well it's great because guys even
if you aren't raw foodist you can always
add more raw to your diet so check the
bundle out and Chris thanks so much it
was great seeing you it's almost
midnight time for you to get to bed and
eat that tomorrow
thank you so much Chef Adrian really
appreciate you being a part in all you
do and bringing us all on your show
honestly I'm so inspired by you and how
active and consistent you are doing or
doing I was just watching I think it was
either like 3 000 episode
2500 but I will get okay for sure yeah I
was just watching that with calling Dr
Colin Campbell and it's like yeah you're
just you're so inspiring I love what
you're doing and I really really feel
blessed that you're a part of this and
allowing us to come on your show I'm
thinking of doing this for either five
years or five thousand episodes
whichever comes first
that's exciting that's amazing I I know
how much time it takes to put to do this
stuff and and yeah the amount of work
and the amount of videos you put out is
just incredible well thank you Chris and
thanks all of you for watching another
episode of Chef AJ live please come back
tomorrow at 11 A.M well actually 9 A.M
Pacific time I forgot we've got a Bonus
show Jill Dalton she's going to be
making Magic Cookie Bars and another
fabulous recipe and then 11 A.M it's
food addiction Friday with Dr Joe
nifflin I want to show you guys my new
manual those are fancy since you're
doing that I'll show my banana mustache
that's adorable I've never seen that
yeah it's my my little teeny bananas I
got them on a whim walking down the
street in New York with a past
girlfriend we're walking down the street
and we're like let's get a tattoo I'm
like what should we do banana mustache a
couple hours later was done that's
actually very clever I've never seen
that so guys if you're listening on
iTunes you're gonna have to check it out
on YouTube to see what we both just said
all right Chris good night take care and
see everyone tomorrow bye-bye goodbye
thank you so much thank you